Guide to the Montana Fish and Game Commission Records 1901-1966
Montana Historical Society
Montana Fish and Game Commission Records
1901-1966
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 125
Montana Fish and Game Commission
6.8 linear feet of shelf space
These records (1901-1966) of the Montana Fish and Game Commission consist of financial records; legal documents regarding the removal of State Fish Game Warden J. S. McFarland; reports; subject files on Flint Creek, the Montana Search and Rescue Association, and various test projects; and miscellany, including journals for state fish spawning stations and hatcheries, blueprints and architectural drawings for Lewis and Clark Caverns, license registers (1913-1919, 1921-1924), confiscation registers (1929-1939, 1942-1950), case records (1924-1939), and docket registers (1901-1938).
The Board of Game and Fish Commissioners was established in March of 1895 to oversee licensing and hunting practices in the state. The Board was comprised of three commissioners, appointed by the Governor and was empowered to appoint a State Fish and Game Warden. The warden also served as secretary and business agent of the Board. The first warden was chosen in 1898. The Board was abolished in 1901, but the functions were assumed by the State Fish Commissioners in 1907. The State Fish Commissioners consisted of a the Warden and two commissioners. By 1911 two more commissioners were added. In 1921 the third Fish and Game Commission formed with five commissioners entrusted to elect the State Warden. In 1972 the Department of Fish and Game was established. It was renamed the Department of Fish, Wildlife and Parks in 1979.
These records consist of financial records, including audit reports; legal documents regarding the removal of State Fish and Game Warden J. S. McFarland; reports; subject files regarding Flint Creek, fish test projects, and the Montana Search and Rescue Association; and miscellany, including journals for state fish spawning stations and hatcheries; blueprints and architectural drawings of Lewis and Clark Caverns, formerly Morrison Cave; case records of regulation violations; confiscation registers; license registers; and docket registers.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Environmental policy--Montana; Fish-culture--Montana; Fish populations--Montana; Game wardens--Montana; Picture-writing--Montana; Search and rescue operations--Montana; Wildlife conservation--Montana--Law and legislation
Alvord Lake (Mont.); Flint Creek (Mont.); Hebgen Lake (Mont.); Lewis and Clark Caverns State Park (Mont.); Libby (Mont.); Libby (Mont.)
Montana; Fisheries and Wildlife
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Financial Records
  - Audit reports, 1933-1966 (Box-folder 1 / 1-4)
  - Register of receipts and disbursements, 1924-1927 (Box-folder Vol / 6)
  - Miscellaneous (re James W. Corey), 1933-1936 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Legal Documents
  - In the matter of the removal of J.S. McFarland, State Fish and Game Warden: Briefs, 1943 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - In the matter of the removal of J.S. McFarland, State Fish and Game Warden: Exhibits, 1943 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
- Reports
  - Report of State Fish and Game Commission, 1941 April - September (Box-folder 2 / 3)
- Subject Files
  - DC shocker tests, 1953-1958 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Flint Creek (re test stream project), 1957, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Flint Creek stomach samples, 1954-1955, 1958 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - TDS growth studies (includes "Electrical Conductivity and Trout Growth Rates in Montana" by Jack Bailey), 1958-1960 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Test stream: barricades, 1953-1956 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Test stream project, 1953-1960 (Box-folder 2 / 9-10)
  - Test stream: shockers (includes "Collecting Fish with Electricity" by V. K. Roberts), 1954-1958 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Montana Search and Rescue Association, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - P. A. Young: Gallatin Petrified Forest, Square Butte "spook rocks," and pictograph caves (includes photographs), 1932-1940 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
- Miscellany
  - Case records of regulation violations, 1914-1939 (Box-folder Vol / 7-21)
  - Confiscations (of illegally harvested game), 1942-1950 (Box-folder Vol / 22)
  - Confiscations (of illegally harvested game), 1929-1939 (Box-folder Vol / 34)
  - Docket registers, 1901-1938 (Box-folder Vol / 35-38)
  - Hunting and fishing license stubs (Montana residents), 1926 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - Hunting and fishing license stubs (Montana residents), 1926 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - Lewis and Clark Caverns (formerly Morrison Cave; includes blueprints and architectural drawings; MAP CASE), circa 1938-1964 (Box-folder 2 / OVSZ)
  - License register, 1913-1919, 1920-1924 (Box-folder Vol / 23-33)
  - Spawning station journals: Alvord Lake (near Troy), 1934-1948 (Volume Vol. 1)
  - Spawning station journals: Libby Fish Hatchery, 1930-1945 (Volume Vol. 2)
  - Spawning station journals: Libby Fish Hatchery, 1945-1956 (Volume Vol. 3)
  - Spawning station journals: Madison (near Hebgen Lake), 1933-1943 (Volume Vol. 4)
  - Spawning station journals: Madison (near Hebgen Lake), 1943-1947 (Volume Vol. 5)